Guide to the Julius Edelstein papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Julius Edelstein Papers,
1917-1963
[Bulk Dates: 1948-1958]
Edelstein, Julius C. C. (Julius Caius Caesar), 1912-2005.
76.11 linear ft. (141 document boxes, 33 index card boxes )
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
6910238
Julius Caesar Claude Edelstein (1912-2005), served as advisor and executive assistant to military officials and political figures. His papers primarily encompass his job as executive assistant and chief of legislative staff to Senator Herbert H. Lehman during Lehman’s senatorial years 1949-1956. Edelstein remained executive assistant to former senator Lehman from 1957-1960. His files include correspondence, memoranda, press releases, clippings, speeches, statistics, maps, pamphlets and government publications.Julius Caesar Claude Edelstein (1912-2005), served as advisor and executive assistant to military officials and political figures. His papers primarily encompass his job as executive assistant and chief of legislative staff to Senator Herbert H. Lehman during Lehman’s senatorial years 1949-1956. Edelstein remained executive assistant to former senator Lehman from 1957-1960. His files include correspondence, memoranda, press releases, clippings, speeches, statistics, maps, pamphlets and government publications..
Biographical Note
Julius C. C. Edelstein was born in Milwaukee, Wisconsin on February 29, 1912. He studied at the University of Wisconsin from 1927-1934 (Law and Medicine), supporting himself through nespaper reporting. In 1937 he began working for the United Press covering U.S. territories and island possessions. His career in journalism continued until World War II when he secured an ensign's commission in the U.S. Navy. After training as a communications officer, he became assistant naval aide to Admiral William D. Leahy, later being promoted to naval aide. Between 1945 and 1947 he served as public affairs advisor to the U.S. High Commissioner to the Philippines, Paul V. McNutt, and as personal advisor to the President of the Philippines, Manuel Roxas. In 1949, Edelstein became Senator Herbert H. Lehman's executive assistant and chief of legislative staff.
Senator Herbert H. Lehman believed in the ability of government to help those that can not help themselves. He fought for civil rights, displaced persons, affordable housing and voted against the popular anti-immigrant legislation. He was responsible for various social reforms such as minimum wage, unemployment insurance, public housing, medical care for the disabled and labor laws to protect workers. Edelstein championed these causes and became personally involved as well, researching and corresponding with numerous democratic constituents' and political figures. He was also a trustee of the National Committee on Immigration and Citizenship (NCIC), secretary for the New York Committee for Democratic Voters and a member of the American Jewish Congress, American Jewish Committee and Americans for Democratic Action (ADA).
In 1955, Edelstein married Rivka Ben-David. In 1956, Julius and Rivka's daughter Suzy was born. Rivka was an assistant military attaché to the Israeli Embassy in Washington. Edelstein continued to serve Lehman until 1960. In 1962, Edelstein became executive assistant to Mayor Robert F. Wagner.
While under Mayor Wagner, he served as executive secretary of the city's antipoverty board. When Robert F. Kennedy ran for the Senate, Mayor Wagner lent Mr. Edelstein to advise him on Jewish and Israeli issues. In 1965, Edelstein embarked on a career at the City University of New York (CUNY). He served as senior vice chancellor of CUNY until 1984 when he retired. He was the primary force behind open admissions at CUNY in the late 1960s, fighting for the economically disadvantaged so as to ensure they had access to an undergraduate education. In 2005, at the age of 93, Julius Edelstein died at New York Hospital.
Scope and Content
This collection holds the papers of Julius C. C. Edelstein. The records that comprise this collection primarily encompass the years in which Edelstein acted as executive assistant and Chief of Legislative Staff to Senator Herbert H. Lehman, 1949-1956. He remained Lehman's assistant through 1960. The records are primarily political in nature although there is personal correspondence of Edelstein's included. The subjects found throughout the collection are agriculture, appropriations, civil rights, civil service, defense, foreign policy and aid, health, housing, immigration, internal security, labor, minimum wage, St. Lawrence project, social security and welfare, tideland offshore oil, tariffs, taxes and veterans. The types of records that can be found are correspondence, pamphlets, government publications, clippings, press releases, statistics, maps and memoranda.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in nine series.
Series I: Bills, 1950-1956
Series II. Campaigns, 1934-1960
Series III. Correspondence, 1923-1960 (1950-1960)
Subseries III.1: Alphabetical, 1954-1960
Subseries III.2: Chronological, 1950-1960
Subseries III.3: Personal, 1923-1959
Series IV. Office Files, 1932-1956 (1950-1955)
Series V. Personal Research Files, 1928-1961
Series VI. Speeches, 1952-1957
Series VII. ubject Files, 1917-1958 (1948-1953)
Series VIII. Indexed Address Cards, undated
Series IX. 2009 Accession, 1952-1963
Subjects
American Civil Liberties Union.; American Jewish Congress.; Americans for Democratic Action.; Democratic National Committee (U.S.); Jewish Telegraphic Agency.; North Atlantic Trade Organization.; Republican Party (1854-present); United Nations.; United States.--Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government (1947-1949); United States.--Defense Production Act of 1950.; United States.--Immigration and Nationality Act.; United States.--Dept. of Health and Human Services.; United States.--Congress.--Joint Committee on Atomic Energy.; United States.--Congress.--Senate--Cloture.; United States.--Congress.--Senate--Rules and practice.; United States.--Securities and Exchange Commission.; United States.--Veterans Administration.; Alinsky, Saul David, 1909-1972.; Benton, William, 1900-1973.; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959.; Eastland, James O. (James Oliver), 1904-1986.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Ewing, Oscar R. (Oscar Ross), 1899-1980.; Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1904-1979.; Fordham, Jefferson Barnes.; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986.; Hennings, Thomas Carey, 1903-1960.; Hill, Lister, 1894-1984.; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986.; Kefauver, Estes, 1903-1963.; Lamont, Corliss, 1902-1995.; Landers, Ann.; Lehman, Herbert H. (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963.; Levy, Beryl Harold, 1908-; Marcantonio, Vito, 1902-1954.; McCarran, Pat, 1876-1954.; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Russell, Richard B. (Richard Brevard), 1897-1971.; Stern, Julius David, 1886-1971.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Sweeney, Esther Emerson, 1905-; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Walter, Francis E. (Francis Eugene), 1894-1963.; Eklutna Dam (Alaska); Europe--Ethnic relations--History--20th century.; Great Lakes (North America)--Regulation.; Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.); Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.)--Regulation.; Saint Lawrence Seaway; United States--Emigration and immigration--Government policy.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; Mutual security program, 1951-; Agriculture.; Antisemitism.; Campaign literature.; Civil issues.; Civil rights.; Communism--United States.; Economic assistance, American--Developing countries.; Electric power production--Great Lakes (North America); Emigration and immigration law--United States--History.; Economic assistance.; International relations.; Hydroelectric power plants--Alaska--Anchorage region.; Hydroelectric power plants--New York (State)--Niagara Falls.; Hydrogen bombs--Moral and ethical aspects.; Immigration.; Insurance, Health--United States.; Internal security--United States.; Juvenile delinquency.; Labor laws and legislation--United States.; Nuclear energy--Law and legislation--United States.; Offshore oil industry.; Price regulation--United States.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Europe.; Refugees.; Subversive activites--United States.; Taxation--United States.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Suzy E. E. Edelstein Gift 2006 2007-2008-M51
Gift of Suzy E. E. Edelstein, 2006
- Series I: Bills, 1950-1956
  This series contains both public and private bills introduced or co-introduced, by Herbert H. Lehman. Also found are amendments, drafts and senate resolutions regarding bills. The topics of the bills are immigration, juvenile delinquency and social security.
  - Amendments--Social Security Act of 1955, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Congressional Record Insertions, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 82nd Congress, 1st Session, 1950-1951, 1953, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - 82nd Congress, 2nd Session, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 83rd Congress, 1st Session, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Refugee Relief, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Immigration, 1950, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Juvenile Delinquency, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - New England-New York Resources Survey Commission, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Senate Concurrent Resolutions, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Senate Joint Resolutions, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Senate Resolutions, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Campaign Files, 1934-1960 (1949-1960)
  Files on the campaign years 1950, 1954, 1956 and 1960 are contained here. In 1949, Lehman was elected US Senator, replacing Robert F. Wagner who retired before his term expired due to ill health. In 1950, Lehman was reelected US Senator for a full 6 year term. Lehman campaigned vigorously for the presidential elections of 1952, 1956 and 1960, supporting Stevenson in 1952 and 1954 and Kennedy in 1960. In 1954, Lehman supported Wagner for New York City Mayor and Harriman for Governor.
  - 1950 Campaign
    - General, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Agriculture and Dairy, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Amendments to Reclamation Project Act of 1939, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Background Materials, 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Campaign Ideas and Clippings, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Candidates for Governor, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1950 July-November (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Democratic Campaign Kit, 1948, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Dewey, Thomas E.--Speeches, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Engel, Irving M.--Speeches Prepared by Beryl H. Levy, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Ewing, Oscar R.--Speeches and Clippings, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Foreign Affairs, 1950, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - Hanley, Joseph R.--Speeches and Biography, 1950, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Indians, 1943, 1945, 1948, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Internal Security--Clippings, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - International Ladies Garment Workers’ Union, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Korea, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Legislative Materials--Central Valley Project, 1949-1950, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Legislative Materials
      - Commodity Credit Corporation, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 1.)
      - Defense Production Bill, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Excise Taxes, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Fur Products Labeling Act, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Preservation of Fort Caroline Settlement, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Rivers and Harbors Control, 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Social Security, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Social Security, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Lehman, Herbert H.
      - Bank Speeches, 1950, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Foreign Policy Speeches, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Speech Drafts, 1950, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Speech Drafts I, 1950, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Speech Drafts II, 1950, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Speeches for Re-election to the US Senate, 1950 September-November, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
      - Voting Record, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Marcantonio, Vito A.--Clippings, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - New York Politics, 1949-1950, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
    - Political Platforms, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Power, 1934-1935, 1948-1950 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Press Lists, 1949-1950 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Press Releases and Statements, 1950 September-November (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Speeches by Herbert H. Lehman Outside of the Senate (Non-Campaign), 1950 January-June, December (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Speeches Made on Behalf of Herbert H. Lehman, 1950 October-November (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - United Nations Week Kit, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1952 Campaign
    - General, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - General Political, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - The Candidates
      - General, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1948-1952 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Harriman, Averell, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Kefauver, Estes, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - McMahon, Brian, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Russell, Richard B., 1952 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Stevenson, Adlai, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Taft, Robert A., 1952 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1951-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
    - Democratic Campaign Kit, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Democratic National Convention (DNC)--Rules, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Democratic State Convention--General, 1952 (Folder 8)
      - Lists of People, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Domestic Issues--Spending, Taxes and Inflation, 1951-1953 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Domestic Policy--General, 1952 (Folder 11)
      - Agriculture, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Civil Liberties, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Civil Rights and Nationalities, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Dairy, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Foreign Policy, 1942-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
    - McCarran Committee, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - New York State--Ives-Lehman, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Platform(s)--General, 1950-1952 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Platform(s)
      - General, 1952-1953, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
      - Harriman (Averell) Statements, 1952, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
      - Resources, 1949-1952 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Speeches--Democratic National Convention (DNC), 1951-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
    - Positions, 1952-1953 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Power, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Source Materials, 1951-1953, (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
    - Speech Material, 1949, 1952, (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
    - Stevenson, Adlai, 1952 (Folder 5)
      - Campaign Speeches, 1952 July 21-September 12 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Stevenson, Adlai
      - Campaign Speeches, 1952 September 13-October 25, (4 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
    - Truman, Harry S.--Whistle Stop Speeches, 1952 September 1-October 6 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Truman, Harry S.--Whistle Stop Speeches, 1952 October 7-November 2, (3 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
    - Voting Records, 1947-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
  - 1954 Campaign
    - Civil Rights, 1953-1954 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Fiscal Policy, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Immigration, 1953-1954 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Speeches
      - Harriman, Averell, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Lehman, Herbert H., 1953-1954, (2 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 5-6)
  - 1956 Campaign
    - Akers, Anthony--General, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Alaska, 1955-1956 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Campaign Organization, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Civil Rights Bills, 1955-1956 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Civil Rights Issues, 1955-1956 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Civil Service Retirement Program, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Cloture, 1951-1953, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Communism, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1956, (2 Folders) (Folder 2-3)
      - Regarding Averell Harriman, 1954-1955 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Democratic National Committee (DNC), 1951, 1953, 1955 (Folder 5)
      - 1956 Strategy Dinner, 1955 March 8 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Drafts--Speeches and Statements, 1956, (2 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 7-8)
    - Dulles, John Foster, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Edelstein, Julius C. C.
      - Projects, 1956 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Research, 1955-1956, (2 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 2-3)
      - To Read File, 1956 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Elections Research, 1955-1956 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Foreign Policy,1956 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Highway Bill, 1956 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Hydrogen Bomb, 1956 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - International Labor Organization, 1956 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Israel, 1956, (2 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 10-11)
    - Israeli-Arab Refugees, 1955-1956 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Javits, Jacob--General, 1951, 1956, (2 Folders) (Folder 2-3)
      - Profile in The New Yorker and Time, 1950, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Voting Record, 1953, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Jewish Telegraphic Agency, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Kefauver, Estes, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Legislative Mail, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Lehman, Herbert H.
      - Engagements, 1956 October-November, (2 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 9-10)
      - Statements on Robert Wagner, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - Schedule, 1956 September-November, (2 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
      - Speeches, 1956 August-September (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - New York Democratic History, 1955 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Nixon, Richard M., 1956 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Nixon, Richard M. and Jacob Javits, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Platforms--Source Materials--General, 1956, (2 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 7-8)
    - Platforms--Source Materials--General, 1956 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Civil Rights, 1952-1957, (4 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 2-5)
    - Power Projects, 1956 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Political Issues--Civil Rights, 1956 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Political Projects, 1956 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Racial Discrimination on Military Bases, 1955-1956 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Research from the Democratic National Committee (DNC), 1955 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Pyle, Howard, 1956 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Research Materials, 1956 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Roll Calls, 1956 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Saudi Arabia, 1951, 1956 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC), 1956 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Speeches
      - Drafts on Civil Rights, 1956 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - 1956 November 1-6 (Box 21, Folder 9)
      - Includes Those Not Delivered, 1956 July-October, (2 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 10-11)
      - Stevenson, Adlai, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Wagner, Robert, 1956 September 25-October 22, (2 Folders) (Folder 2-3)
        - Drafts, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Tax Relief Program, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Telephone Lists, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - U.S. Republican Political Party (GOP) on Civil Rights, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Wagner, Robert and the Urban League of Greater New York, 1956 (Folder 8)
      - Positions, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - 1960 Campaign
    - Press Releases--DNC--Fact Sheets, 1960 September-November (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Press Releases
      - DNC--Publicity Division, 1960 September 28-November 4, (4 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 1-4)
      - US Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1960 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - US Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1960, (3 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 1-3)
      - Lehman, Herbert H. as Honorary Chairman of the NY Citizens Committee for Kennedy and Johnson, 1960 September 14-November 5 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - Veteran’s Administration, 1960 June-December, (2 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 5-6)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1923-1960 (1950-1960)
  Series III primarily consists of correspondence directly related to the office of Senator Lehman. The majority of letters address issues surrounding immigration laws in the United States. In November of 1953, Senator Lehman called a meeting where he invited outstanding leaders of various the religious and civic organizations which had expressed concern about the racist aspects of US immigration laws. The group which participated in the meeting set up a steering committee to follow through for the purpose to help organize a campaign with the goal toward educating US citizens about the un-American nature of the country’s immigration policies as designated under the McCarran-Walter Immigration Act. The steering committee set up two subcommittees: one to prepare an outline of the structure and program, and the other to prepare a statement of the policies which the National Committee would adhere. Next, the committee prepared a letter to solicit membership. The letter was mailed in early 1955 to numerous individuals resulting in 350 people accepting membership on the National Committee. The National Committee was granted a charter of incorporation in the spring of 1955 under the New York State Education Law resulting in the formation of the National Committee on Immigration and Citizenship (NCIC). The incorporators were as follows; Spyros S. Skouras, Senator William Benton, F. Ernest Johnson, Philip B. Perlman, Thomas K. Finletter, Theodore R. McKeldin, Daniel Bell and Senator Herbert H. Lehman. In conjunction with the incorporators, the following individuals were on the first board of trustees; Francis B. Sayre, Jr., Rabbi Abba Hillel Silver, John O’Grady, Walter P. Reuther, Roy Williams, Thomas A. Pappas, Jefferson B. Fordham and Jane M. Hoey. The chairman of the Board of Trustees, Spyros Skouras, was unable to devote a sufficient amount of time to the affairs of the Committee so Senator Lehman accepted the chairmanship.
  Throughout all three subseries there is correspondence regarding the NCIC, ADA, American Jewish Congress and American Jewish Committee because of Lehman and Edelstein’s affiliation with these organizations. Office memorandums are abundant, Lehman to Edelstein and the reverse. These are usually the method by which Edelstein briefs Lehman on current news concerning his Senatorial post. The original order of the series consisted of five subseries: two arranged alphabetically, one for the years 1954-1958, and a second for 1960, one chronologically, and two titled “personal correspondence”. This has been maintained with the two alpha files under subseries III.1 and subseries III.3. It should be noted that Edelstein’s personal correspondence can be found in all three subseries.
  - Subseries III.1: Alphabetical, 1954-1960
    Contains letters and memoranda. Political topics addressed: immigration, power projects, campaigns, civil rights, McCarthyism, labor, health and housing. Names that frequently appear are Senator Lister Hill; Edward Marks, Executive Director of the US Committee for Refugees; Jefferson B. Fordham, Dean of the University of Pennsylvania Law School; Michel Cieplinski of the Nationalities Division (Democratic National Committee); V.A. Marcantonio of the American Labor Party; O.R. Ewing, Administrator of the Federal Security Agency; and James T. Farrell, an American novelist.
    - A, 1955-1958 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - B, 1955-1957 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - B1, 1955-1958 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - C, 1955-1958, (2 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 4-5)
    - D, 1955-1958 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - E, 1955-1958 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - E, 1955-1958 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - F, 1955-1958, (2 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 2-3)
    - G, 1955-1958, (2 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 4-5)
    - H, 1955-1958, (2 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 6-7)
    - I, 1955-1958 (Box 26, Folder 8)